Guide to the James Alexander Houston Incoming correspondence, 1845-1849
Department of Special Collections
Houston, James Alexander. Incoming correspondence,
1845-1849
M1171
Houston, James Alexander.
.5 linear ft. (1 manuscript box)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection includes incoming letters sent to James Alexander Houston, a medical doctor, the son and brother of Irish clergymen, and an emigrant from Ireland to the United States before 1845. Familiar with the Pitman method of stenography, Houston reported for both New York and Washington, D.C., newspapers. He had good friends in the American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society, including Gamaliel Bailey and Louis Tappan.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Letts Jones, 1975.
Biography
Much of what we know of this interesting man must be deduced from the letters he received from 1845 to 1849, and from resorting to the Encyclopedia Britannica. From the former source, we know, for example, that he was a medical doctor, the son and brother of Irish clergymen, and an emigré from Ireland to the United States during some period before 1845. We also know that he was married, with sub-teen children, a Presbyterian, and adept at shorthand. A curious combination, a medical man who knew shorthand. But not so curious if a bit of the history of shorthand is noted. According to the Encyclopedia Britannica, various schemes for shorthand date from Greco-Roman times to modern times, including Shelton's system, which was used by Samuel Pepys in his Diaries of 1660. However, stenography reached its developmental zenith in England in the nineteenth century with the publication of Isaac Pitman's method in 1837, which swept the British Isles and America, as well. One of its early uses was the verbatim transcription of clerical sermons for publication. Another was verbatim reporting for newspapers of the day. It was little wonder then that Houston found more work as a shorthand reporter than as Assistant Surgeon of the New York State Militia. The concession of vast amounts of land to the United States after the Mexican War (1848) rekindled the slavery question. Newly elected President Polk, whose views were expressed by the Union newspaper in Washington, D.C., publicly urged Congress to create Oregon, New Mexico, and California as territories, whereupon anti-slavery Congressmen persuaded Democratic Congressman David Wilmot, from Pennsylvania to add an amendment to a $2 million appropriation bill for boundary settlement. The "Wilmot Proviso" stipulated that slavery should not exist in any part of the territory acquired by the United States as a result of the Mexican War. Several times the House passed the amendment but it failed in the Senate. Yet it stimulated active debate between slavery proponents and anti-slavery forces. Throughout the electric days of 1846-47, Houston, the official Stenographer to the U. S. Senate, was kept busy reporting and publishing them in Houston's Journal. Testimonials to his ability and accuracy rained on Houston from Congressmen and the leading eastern newspapers of the day. Dr. Houston also found work on the New York Herald, founded in 1845. In Washington D. C., he reported for the Union, for George Gideon's Republic, and the Era, where he became close friends with its publisher, Gamaliel Bailey. The Era was the organ of the American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society, which began publication in 1844. Houston was also a friend of Louis Tappan, a major figure in anti-slavery ranks and a publisher (co-founder with is brother Arthur of the Journal of Commerce in 1827, and the Emancipator in 1833). Houston divided his time between between Washington and New York depending on the sessions of the Senate, moving in the circles of well known individuals of his time and place-political figures, judges, publishers. However, something seems to have occurred at the end of 1849, when he moves out of the Era offices one step ahead of the sheriff who arrives to attach his belongings for what appears to be a debt. He goes back to New York (see letter of December 12, 1849, from James W. Simonton). Perhaps his debt was settled, for the last letters of 1849, have him successfully applying to George Gideon for work to be sent to Washington D. C.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The collection mainly contains letters to James Alexander Houston from 1845-1849, with a few published testimonials, and autographs of Horace Greeley, George Gideon, Charles A. Dana, and one or two others. The letters are arranged in numerical sequence for the years 1845 to 1949, and by day and month within the sequence of years. A fairly large number of the letters are undated and are filed at the end, with some dates suggested from the context of the letters. All letters are indexed and synopsized.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bailey, Gamaliel.; Tappan, Louis.; American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society.; United States--History--1815-1861.
Collection Contents
- Henry Morris, Washington D.C., to James A. Houston (JAH), in care of the New York Herald.1843 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Please accept more money. The amount enclosed is according to Mr. "S's" orders. Sent to JAH with assurance that Mr.Bennett would see that JAH received the letter.
  Morris, Henry; Bennett,[James Gordon]; New York Herald
- William [Inche ?], New York, to JAH in care of N.Y. Herald office1845 Feb. 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Inche, a friend, asks JAH to find him a job. He is at the Alms House, Bellevue, N.Y.
  Inche, William; New York Herald
- [J. A. Houston?]1845 Dec. 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Partial note
  [J.A Houston ?]
- Henry [Thompson?] to JAH1846 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  He will prepare remarks on "Graduation Bill" for the Union.
  [Thompson?], Henry; The Union
- J. C. Houston,Ballymena, Ireland, to JAH1846, July 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Mixed longhand and shorthand pertaining to family matters.
  Added note in unknown hand "Dr J A Houston had three brothers, John Clarke, Gareth, [both} clergymen, Robert, was a Captain of Marines, U.S. Navy. [JAh] had one sister, Eliza Jane.
  Houston, J. C.
- W. Hunt, House of Representatives, to JAH1847 Feb. 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Testimonial to JAH's transcription ability.
  Hunt, W.; House of Reprentatives
- C. J. Ingersole, House of Representatives, to JAH.1847 Feb, 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Testimonial to JAH's transcription abililty
  Added note in unknown hand says Ingersole was a U.S. Senator [U. S. Concressman ?} and former Governor of Connecticut.
  Ingersole, C. J.; House of Reprsentatives
- M. S. Payne, Rep Hall, to JAH1847 Feb. 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Added note in an unknown hand, 'Ohio.'
  Payne, M. S.
- George Aikman, House of Representatives, to JAH1847 Feb. 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Testimonial to JAh's transcrition ability.
  Aikman, George; House of Representatives
- Ben E. Green, Wahington D. C., to JAH, as "Reporter for The Union"1847 Feb. 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Green understands JAH is being considered for shorthand reportial functions for the Senate, but calls JAH's attention to the mistakes in a recent transcription of his speech in the Union, relative to "Mr. Marks. Asks that they be corrected in tonight'sUnion or he will be obliged to tell the Senate that JAH is not to be depended on.
  Green, Ben E.; The Union newspaper
- G. B. Bailey, Washington, D. C., to JAH1847 Mar. 28 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Instructs JA H to send a weekly letter/editorial to the Era.
  Bailey, G. B.; The Era newspaper
- G. Bailey, Washington D. C., to JAH1847 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Commends JAH on his letters to the Era.
  Bailey, G.; The Era
- R. C. Wetmore to JAH, Broadway [NY ?]1847 Apr. 21 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Please call for money due on charges for reporting the "Festival." Thanks very much.
  Wetmore, R. C.
- G. Bailey, Washington, D. C., to JAH1847 Jun. 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Bailey is pleased with letter for the Era from JAH. How would JAH like to do a column for the Era ?
  Bailey, G; The Era newspaper
- J. Marshall, New York, to JAH1847 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  The Graenfenberg Health Manual is delayed and will not be published until some later time.
  Graefenberg Company, 50 Broadway, New York
- J. Marshall, New York, to JAH1847 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Qwing to a temporary misunderstanding we have to delay the publication of the Graefenberg Health Manual.
  Marshall, J.; Graefenberg Company, 50 Broadway, New York; Graefenberg Heath Manual
- Clarke Houston, Ballybarkey, Ireland,to JAH, "Stenographer to U.S. Senate"1847 Aug. 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Clarke Houston [father of James Alexander Houston] writes of family matters. Also reccomends "Mr. Peake", and hopes JAH can be of service to Mr Peake.
  Houston, Clarke; The Era newspaper
- Eliza Houston, Ballymena, Ireland, to JAH 1847 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Family matters
  Added in unknown hand: " J's mother"
  Houston, Eliza
- Simon Harker, Liverpool, to JAH1847 Sept. 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Harker saw JAH's ad in The Union for a reporter for the next session of the U. S. Senate, and wants to apply. Cites his qualifications.
  Harker, Simon; The Union newspaper; thr Liverpool Journal
- W.W. Veaho, Ballymena, Ireland, to JAH 1847 Sept. 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Asks JAH to help his son, Henry, if he comes to America.
  Henry Veaho
- Thomas DeWitt, New York, to JAH1847 Oct. 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  States that his sermon does not represent the discourse as delivered. Phraseaology is different. But h;e considers it well done in "full sketch."
  New York, settlement by Dutch, 1624.; Sermons in Dutch and in English.
- Prosper Wetmore, New York, to JAH1847 Dec. 13 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Wetmore says he is sorry not to have answered JAH's letter before. Is happy to be of service. Does not know what vacancies exist [in the Navy ?], but JAH can probably find out from the Navy Department.
  Added note in unknown hand says Wetmore is the U.S. Navy agent for the Nicaragua Steamship Line.
  Nicaragua Steamship Line
- John C. Fitzpatrick to JAH, "reporter to the U.S. Senate."1847 Dec. 24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Fitzpatrick makes an index of the sessions of the Senate.for JAH. For a "consideration" he will make a copy for JAH
- W. L. Shuttleworth, Washington D. C. (U.S. Hotel), to JAH1848 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  He is returning JAH's shawl.
- D. Pope.New York, to JAH.1848 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Discusses the cost of various papers in various amounts.
- Charles E. Ball to JAH1848 Jan. 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Salutation calls JAH "Bro. Houston." Writer sends JAH "rough sketch" of proceedings of Disrict 10, presumably for publication.
- John Clarke Houston, Newcastle-on-Tyne, to JAH1848 Feb. 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  John Clarke Houston, JAH's brother, discusses family matters. Refers to "Joseph" and their brother, Robert. Mentions JAH is to visit them soon.
- Hon. James W. Bradbury to William Johnson.1848 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Writer wishes to know, from JAH, answers to questions on how many words he can write in a minute while "following a speaker," what amount of practic is needed to reach that level of proficiency, can a shorthand manuscript be used with the same facility as it it were written, and what are the comparative merits of stenography and phonography, and which does JAH use ?
  Added note in unknown hand says that either James W. Bradbury [or Wm T. Johnson] is from Middlesex Connecticut, is a law reporter ( 1770 to 1848), and is on the Supreme Court.
- Mr [Steit ?] to JAH1848 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Testamonial to his ability evidenced in recent report.
- ?, Cincinnatti, to JAH1848 Jun. 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Regrets JAH did not attend convention. "It has decided Ohio against Taylor." Slavery versus anti-slavery politics discussion.
  Zachary Taylor; Martin Van Buren; Slavery; Anti-slavery; Ohio
- [Henry ?] O'Riellly,Washington, to JAH1848 Jul. 30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Please accept the enclosed certificates.
  Telegraph System
- G. B. Moss, Washington D.C., to JAH at Brown's Hotel1848 Oct. 12 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Pleae arramge to buy writer the "London Encyclopedia (English edition)". Get it for $25 or less. Writer will send JAH a draft on H. O'Rielly.
  Thomas Cowperthwaite, Philadelphia
- W. A. Kennedy, Washington, D. C., to JAH1848 Oct. 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Don't pay your recent foreman, "Wilkinson", as he is in debt to writer. He also appropriated money from "Laurens" also in JAH employee, and used it for his own use.
- G. Bailey, Washington D. C., to JAH1848 Nov.7 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Discussion of money owed and accounting matters.
  The Era newspaper
- Joseph W.Dennis, New York, to G. Bailey1848 Nov. 9 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Charged JAH for more bundles of papers that the man got from JAH
- S,.D. Figham, New Hope, to JAH, Washington D.C.1848 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Thank you for the U.S. Senate report.
- David [ Sessions?], to JAH.1848 Nov. 24 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Am sending another manuscript.
- James W, Simonton, Washington, to JAH1848 Dec. 12 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Simonton reports that Mt. Rives says "Wheeler & Miles need no help until after the holidays. " Fowler & Leeds have no engagement." "The Union has contracted with M. Parkhurst of Boston." Simonton "has done his best to remove prejudice against you in Washington." He will dispose of JAH's thing from the Era office. He offers his services to JAH.
  Added note in an unknown hand states Simonton is a noted newsman of the time.
  Wheeler and Miles; Fowler and Leeds; M. Parkhurst; The Union newspaper; The Era newspaper
- Anthony [Bantery?]New York, to JAH1848 Dec. 14 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Writer will come late to New York Scottish Guard Ball.
  New York Scottish Guard
- G.B Moss, Washington, D. C., to JAH (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Writer is certain that their differences can be ironed out in an interview.
- James W. Simonton, Washinton, D. C., to JAH1848 Dec. 31 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  All of JAH's books will be sent by express to New York. Writer will send accounts and disbursements. Please write if you are disposed to.
- G. Bailey, Washington D.C., to JAH[?,?] 1848 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  A sheriff came to the office to attach JAH's things. Wilkinson had eloped with Henry's money, and is now in New York City, at Mckay, 120 Prince Street. Bailey has guaranteed everything till JAH comes or answers at once. JAH's documents are in danger. JAH also ows bailey $191. The draft will reach Bailey at the Merchants Bank, New York.
  Wilkinson; The Era newspaper
- JAH Accounts, January to September, 18481848 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  List of JAH accounts re paper and labor, January to September 1848
- Thomas Macaulay, Belfast, Ireland, to JAH, 1849 Jan 12 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Chides JAH jocularly for having "repeatedly neglected to show me any kindness." Congraulates JAH on his work. Says Francis Finlay, the Whig... "speaks very harshly of Bennett" who, in a visit to Ireland, "allowed himself to be rejected by [ John] O'Connell."
  [James Gordon] Bennett]; Francis Finlay; [John] O'Connell; The New York Herald
- William C. Lantzinger, Washington D.C., to JAH1849 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Remarks that a Couriers Passport would not do much for JAH. The rules for individuals bearing despatches are strict about proceeding directly to the destination.
- John Bryant, Washington D.C., to JAH, New York1849 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  John Bryant, Jr., Treasurer of the 4th Presbyterian Church, writes JAH notifying him that he is in arrears in his pew rent.
- Charles B. Spicer, Colonel, New York, to JAH Lexington Ave and 26th Street, New York1849 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Regimental order naming James Alexander Houston to be Assistant Surgeon of the Second Regiment, New York State Milita.
  Note in unknown hand names the Adjutant signing the order to be William [Postty?], and makes mention that [Eugene Alex ?]
  Houston was commissioned by Governor Cleveland to be Assist. Surgeon of 4th [__?__] Co., N. Y. S. N. Y., 1880
  William C. [Postty ?]; New York State Militia, Second Regiment
- H. M. Garland, Jr., Baltimore, to JAH, Washington D.C.1849 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  In the interest of speeding up work he may move his office to Washington,D. C. which is at the end of the "Northern Line" and the end of the "Southern Line" [telegraph line ?]. Could he not join JAH as a reporter from either Washington or Baltimore for the next session of Congress?
  America [Packet Ship]; The New York Herald
- G. Bailey, Washington, D.C., to JAH. 1849 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Writer asks if JAH is going to Europe this spring, and has he decided the that the writer can do JAH's work in his absence ?
- David [Seveves ?], Washinton, D. C. to JAH1849 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Informs JAH that the suit is won in Lee vs Houston, and renders his bill.
- S. B. Wylie, Philadelphia, to JAH1849 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Friend of JAH"s father requests JAH intercede to arrange for discharge of an Irish boy, Samuel Smith, who joined the marines and now wants a discharge/
  Hugh Smith; Samuel Smith
- Geo A. Gideon, Washington D. C., to JAH. New York1849 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Writer requests JAH to tell him what he expects to pay for "a letter every day "? Hurry, "we commence on June 13."
- Geo. A. Gideon, Washington D. C., to JAH1849 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Writer accepts terms ($10/week) and, "you must give us the first letter for Wednesdaty morning's paper so it must reach here by Tuesday evening."
- Wm. C. Lantzinger to JAH, New York1849 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  JAH in arrears for membership of Masonic Lodge. Writer placed JAh's case before members and was selected to arrange application for JAH to renew his membership.
  Masonic Lodge, New York
- Geo A. Gideon, Washington D. C., to JAH, New York1849 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  Gideon reminds JAH not to forget the steamship letter. Plus Gideon sends him a check for his letters.
  The Republic newspaper
- Greeley, Horace, New York, to Russell Sturgis, London1858 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Horace Greeley of the New York Tribune introduces friends W.E, Robinson and R. M. Mellis who will visit "on a mission of the 'highest respectability.
  [B________?] Brothers, London, England; New York Tribune